Faculty Organizations
University of Houston Libraries
Faculty Organizations
1951-2005
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
Faculty Organizations, 1951-2005
2.00 Linear Feet
Forms part of the University Archives.
1969-063
Biographical Note
Faculty Association
The Faculty Association of the University of Houston Constitution and By - Laws, adopted
January 20, 1947 outlined the principle purposes as: to foster a bond of fellowship among its members; to promote the progress of the University of Houston; to act as a service organization and open forum, and to direct the operation of the Faculty Club. Membership was limited to full time faculty, including research faculty of the University of Houston whose duties were primarily non-administrative.
On November 19, 1962, a faculty committee concluded that the first three parts of the Faculty Association Constitution were being served by the Faculty Senate, and that the sole purpose of the Faculty Associates seemed to be; "To direct the operation of the Faculty Club." The merger Committee recommended the amalgamation of the two associations and that a committee composed of the Chairman of the two organization plus two members at large be appointed to rewrite the constitution and by laws of the new organization to be named: University of Houston Faculty Club.
Faculty Assembly
The Faculty Assembly consisted of almost 100 representatives from the institutional department and colleges, with the number of representatives varying from four to one, depending upon the student enrollment within the component involved. The Assembly had an elected president and secretary, a 14-person Faculty Council with its own Chairman, Vice-Chairman, and representative to the Executive Council; and an eight-person Steering Committee. Dr. T.C. Sinclair stated that the purpose of the Faculty Assembly would be to create a "real faculty community of scholars" and that the work of the Assembly would be carried on largely by committees.
Faculty Senate
Faculty Senate adopted its formal Constitution in May 1961, with the goal of providing
"an instrument for cooperative action in attaining such ends as the member may select." The Faculty Senate reorganized, freely, in 1962 at the beginning of the Hoffman administration and formed several new committees including a Committee on University Committees, Student Life, Educational Policy, and Faculty Affairs. The first official faculty handbook was also completed during this period. The Faculty Senate consists of 52 permanent members elected by the faculty.
Shared governance is now a major goal of the organization and is defined by the Faculty Senate as the "collective commitment of the faculty and administration at the University of Houston to work cooperatively, together with the University Constituencies, to achieve a common vision of excellence for the University.
Scope and Contents
The Faculty Organizations records primarily consist of organizational minutes. The records arrived at the archives in relatively good order, which has been maintained where possible. For preservation and access reasons the collection has been re-boxed and re-foldered. New folder titles conform, as closely as possible, to original folder titles, except when the original was obviously incomplete, incorrect, or confusing. Original folder and item order has been maintained whenever possible. Exceptions were made when folders were obviously misfiled or when no order was apparent.
Forms part of the University Archives.
Arrangement of Materials
The collection has been divided into three sub-series; Faculty Association, Faculty Assembly, and the Faculty Senate, with the materials placed into chronological order.
Related Materials
Terms are either Library of Congress Subject Headings or taken from local sources.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
University of Houston; University of Houston -- Faculty Senate
Genre/Form of Material:
Minutes
Access Restrictions
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Detailed Description
- Faculty Association Minutes
  This series consists of 10 folders in chronological order and date from 1954-1963. The 1959 Constitution and By-Laws of the organization is also included with this series.
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Association-Constitution and By-Laws, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Association Minutes, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Faculty Assembly Minutes
  This series consists of eight folders and date from 1951-1959.
  - Faculty Assembly, 1951-1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1955-1956 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1955-1956 (continued) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Standards Committee of the Faculty Assembly, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Assembly Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Faculty Senate Minutes
  This series consists of 30 folders and date from 1969-2005.
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2001 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Faculty Senate Minutes, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)